<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>learning on sysid blog</title>
    <link>/blog/learning/</link>
    <description>Recent content in learning on sysid blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2022, sysid.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/blog/learning/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>BMW I4 and linear dynamic Truchet tilings</title>
      <link>/bmw-i4-and-linear-dynamic-truchet-tilings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/bmw-i4-and-linear-dynamic-truchet-tilings/</guid>
      <description>Isn&amp;rsquo;t this BMW I4 a beauty? The perfect motivation to start a journey into a little optimization problem:
How to manipulate traditional Truchet tiles so that the resulting tiling resembles the Ultimate Driving Machine?
Truchet tiles are a well known niche in math because they form a foundation for a lot of interesting questions. The basic theory: You have four simple tiles:
Since every tile is 50% black and 50% white a resulting tiling can only resemble a grey area if viewed from afar.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Energy Forecast for a full-scale Vehicle Plant</title>
      <link>/energy-forecast-for-a-full-scale-vehicle-plant/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 May 2017 22:12:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/energy-forecast-for-a-full-scale-vehicle-plant/</guid>
      <description>Energy Forecast for a full scale Vehicle Plant Energy forecasting is based on time series analysis. There are many techniques for analysing and forecasting time series, e.g. ARIMA, linear regression and deep learning. To tackle the challenge at hand a linear regression will be the benchmark model aganst which deep learning models will be tested. In particular a multi layer perceptron (MLP) and recurrent neural network (RNN), i.e. Long-Short Time Memory (LSTM) model will be applied.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Machine Learning Journey</title>
      <link>/machine-learning-journey/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2017 22:12:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/machine-learning-journey/</guid>
      <description>Cheat Sheet General Explanations: embeddings: a way to translate multidimensional input into fixed length log dimensional representations: lookup the integer index of the object and look it up in a corresponding matrix wich holds the low-dim representation. If no embeddings are used, the input has to be one-hot-encoded wich yields huge matrices KFold Cross Validation: The purpose of cross-validation is model checking, not model building. Once we have used cross-validation to select the better performing model, we train that model (whether it be the linear regression or the neural network) on all the data.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
