<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>work on sysid blog</title>
    <link>/blog/work/</link>
    <description>Recent content in work on sysid blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2022, sysid.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/blog/work/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>developer&#39;s learnings</title>
      <link>/developers-learnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/developers-learnings/</guid>
      <description>Adages collected over time Simple is not given. It takes constant work There is no pride in managing or understanding complexity Typed languages are essential on teams with mixed experience levels Java is a great language because it&amp;rsquo;s boring Frontend development is a nightmare world of Kafkaesque awfulness I no longer enjoy Good management is invaluable. Objects are extremely good at what they&amp;rsquo;re good at. Blind devotion to functional is dumb.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>rsnip</title>
      <link>/rsnip/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/rsnip/</guid>
      <description>Fast, Reliable, Yours: Why Snippets Outshine LLMs for boring Tasks While large language models (LLMs) like ChatGPT are revolutionizing workflows with their smart completions and contextual insights, you don’t want to re-research a command or script every time you need it.
Why does a good snippet manager still matter? Even in an age of intelligent assistants, there’s a compelling case for a specialized and fast snippet manager:
Speed: LLMs are slow when it comes to re-fetching familiar snippets.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rewriting a Vim Plugin in Rust: vimania-uri-rs</title>
      <link>/rewriting-a-vim-plugin-in-rust-vimania-uri-rs/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/rewriting-a-vim-plugin-in-rust-vimania-uri-rs/</guid>
      <description>Advanced URI Handling for the Modern Vim User
Why? Vim&amp;rsquo;s native gx command is somehow limited in its flexibility and capabilities. I wanted more powerful URI handling capabilities, which led me to create vimania-uri, a Vim plugin designed to provide advanced URI management within Vim.
However, while the plugin achieved its goal in terms of functionality, it came with a performance penalty: the initial loading of the plugin&amp;rsquo;s Python dependencies severely impacted Vim&amp;rsquo;s startup times.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Select Points</title>
      <link>/select-points/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/select-points/</guid>
      <description>Given multiple sets of data points. Select one point per set so that the distances between the points is minimal.1
Model Non-convex MIQP Model $$ \min \sum_{i,j| ok_{i,j}} dist_{i,j} \cdot x_i \cdot x_j \\ \sum_{i|group_{i,g}} x_i = 1 \forall g \\ x_i \in {0,1} $$
Linear MIP Model To linearize the model a standard procedure can be applied:
Let&amp;rsquo;s introduce a new binary variable, $z_{i,j}$, that represents the product of the binary variables $\color{darkred}x_i$ and $\color{darkred}x_j$.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>vimania-uri</title>
      <link>/vimania-uri/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/vimania-uri/</guid>
      <description>Double-click-&amp;gt;Open. But for VIM. No mouse.
Key Features Open URIs, html, docx, pptx, jpg, png, mp3, &amp;hellip; Handle almost any URI Paste URLs with human-friendly description vimania-uri
Why? One magic power of OS UI is the capability of opening URIs by just double-clicking. As CLI worker using a mouse does not cut it.
Markdown Plugin To deal with markdown a plugin is helpful, e.g. plasticboy&amp;rsquo;s plugin.
It allows to create new files by adding a link [topic](topic) and then jump to it by typing ge while the cursor is on the link.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Software Architecture 2022</title>
      <link>/software-architecture-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/software-architecture-2022/</guid>
      <description>A refresher in software architecture philosophies with Perseverance, Patience and Python.
This is a high-speed overflight over current approaches with an occasional deep dive.
CRUD, MVC simple concepts and therefore effective communication in dev teams works as expected. Limits known, e.g. modelling complex business domains DDD and Clean Architecture structure of software logic reflects business processes ubiquitous language as common communication ground for developer and business concepts like Aggregate and UnitOfWork provide clear consistency and concurrency model.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Job Shop Scheduling Problem</title>
      <link>/job-shop-scheduling-problem/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/job-shop-scheduling-problem/</guid>
      <description>The Job Shop Scheduling Problem (JSSP) is an NP-hard problem. 1
The JSSP is defined by a set of jobs that must be executed by a set of machines in a specific order for each job. Each job has a defined execution time for each machine and a defined processing order of machines. Also, each job must use each machine only once. The machines can only execute a job at a time and once started, the machine cannot be interrupted until the completion of the assigned job.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dispersion</title>
      <link>/dispersion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/dispersion/</guid>
      <description>Find 10 points out of 50 with maximum distance from each other.1
This problem can modelled as a max-min model where we maximize the smallest distance of 10 points.
Model $$ \max \Delta\\ s.t.\\ \Delta \le d_{i,j} + M(1- x_i x_j), \forall i \lt j \\ \sum_i x_i = k\\ x_i \in {0,1}\\ $$
M is an upper bound on the distances: $$ M = \max_{i\le j} d_{i,j}\\ $$</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
