<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>development on sysid blog</title>
    <link>/blog/development/</link>
    <description>Recent content in development on sysid blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <copyright>Copyright © 2022, sysid.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/blog/development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Rust’s Strategic Advantage</title>
      <link>/rusts-strategic-advantage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/rusts-strategic-advantage/</guid>
      <description>The Unexpected Trifecta Three independent forces are reshaping software development, each following its own logic, each seemingly unrelated.
1. Security:
70% of critical vulnerabilities in major platforms stem from memory safety issues, costing billions.
2. Economics:
Data center energy consumption is growing at 12% annually, heading toward 3% of global electricity by 2030, while water consumption for cooling threatens to double or quadruple by 2028.
3. GenAI:
The rise of AI code generation, where training data quality increasingly determines model performance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>bkmr reborn</title>
      <link>/bkmr-reborn/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Aug 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/bkmr-reborn/</guid>
      <description>Streamlining Developer Productivity Store it, find it, act on it.
Developers know the struggle: You&amp;rsquo;re deep into concentration when suddenly you need that specific command, website, or snippet you used weeks ago.
However, what should have been a quick retrieval turns into a disruptive search.
There are many tools, which individually address this issue. But rarely provide a holistic solution.
The Challenge We face a common set of challenges when working with information:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Claude Code Saved My Weekend</title>
      <link>/how-claude-code-saved-my-weekend/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/how-claude-code-saved-my-weekend/</guid>
      <description>If you want something done right, automate it.
Modern Open-Source Maintenance As the maintainer of sse-starlette, my GitHub notifications rarely bring me joy on a lazy Saturday afternoon.
This weekend, I decided to push Claude Code a little bit, hoping to save precious summer time.
Issue #140 didn&amp;rsquo;t just look interesting; it appeared non-trivial, touching on asyncio intricacies, multi-threading, and event-loop handling—elements that typically guarantee headaches.
Rather than my usual deep-dive session of debugging and refactoring, I handed the reins to Claude Code, eager to see if it could manage the problem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>developer&#39;s learnings</title>
      <link>/developers-learnings/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/developers-learnings/</guid>
      <description>Simple is not given. It takes constant work! There is no pride in managing or understanding complexity. Typed languages are essential on teams with mixed experience levels. Java is a great language because it&amp;rsquo;s boring! Objects are extremely good at what they&amp;rsquo;re good at. Blind devotion to functional is dumb. Engineering is about communication. If I think something is easy, that&amp;rsquo;s a sure sign I don&amp;rsquo;t understand it. Very few abstractions exist in general application development.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
